[This talk contains graphic language and descriptions of sexual violence
(تحتوي هذه المحادثة على لغة صادمة ووصف لعنفٍ جنسي،
Viewer discretion is advised]
ينصح بتحفظ المشاهدين)
Tom Stranger: In 1996, when I was 18 years old,
توم سترينجر: في العام 1996، عندما كنت أبلغ من العمر 18 عامًا،
I had the golden opportunity to go on an international exchange program.
أتيحت لي فرصة ذهبية للذهاب في برنامج التبادل الدولي.
Ironically I'm an Australian who prefers proper icy cold weather,
ومن المفارقات أنّني أسترالي أفضل الطقس الجليدي البارد،
so I was both excited and tearful when I got on a plane to Iceland,
لذلك كنت متحمسًا وحزينًا على حدٍ سواء عندما صعدت إلى الطائرة متجهًا لآيسلاندا،
after just having farewelled my parents and brothers goodbye.
بعدما ودعت والديّ وإخوتي.
I was welcomed into the home of a beautiful Icelandic family
استُقبلِت في منزلٍ لأسرة آيسلدنية جميلة
who took me hiking,
الذين اصطحبوني للتنزه،
and helped me get a grasp of the melodic Icelandic language.
وساعدوني على فهم اللغة الأيسلندية الرخيمة.
I struggled a bit with the initial period of homesickness.
عانيت قليلًا خلال الفترة الأولى من الحنين إلى الوطن.
I snowboarded after school,
كنت أتزحلق على الجليد بعد المدرسة،
and I slept a lot.
وأنام كثيرًا.
Two hours of chemistry class in a language that you don't yet fully understand
ساعتان من حصة الكيمياء بلغة لاتفهمها جيدًا بعد
can be a pretty good sedative.
يمكن أن تكون مُنومًا جيدًا جدًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My teacher recommended I try out for the school play,
نصحني أستاذي بأن أشارك في مسرحية المدرسة،
just to get me a bit more socially active.
لكي أصبح اجتماعيًا أكثر.
It turns out I didn't end up being part of the play,
في نهاية الأمر لم أشارك في المسرحية،
but through it I met Thordis.
ولكن من خلالها التقيت (بثورديس).
We shared a lovely teenage romance,
تشاركنا قصة حب جميلة في فترة المراهقة،
and we'd meet at lunchtimes to just hold hands
وكنّا نلتقي في وقت الغداء لنشابك أيدينا فقط
and walk around old downtown Reykjavík.
ونتجوّل في وسط مدينة (ريكيافيك) القديمة.
I met her welcoming family, and she met my friends.
التقيت بأسرتها الودودة، كما التقت هي بأصدقائي.
We'd been in a budding relationship for a bit over a month
كنّا في علاقة ناشئة لأكثر من شهر بقليل
when our school's Christmas Ball was held.
عندما أقيم حفل عيد الميلاد في مدرستنا.
Thordis Elva: I was 16 and in love for the first time.
ثيودرس إليفا: كنت في السادسة عشرة ومغرمة للمرة الأولى.
Going together to the Christmas dance
ذهابنا سويًة لرقصة عيد الميلاد
was a public confirmation of our relationship,
كان تأكيدًا علنيًا على علاقتنا.
and I felt like the luckiest girl in the world.
وشعرت بأنّني الفتاة الأكثر حظًا في العالم.
No longer a child, but a young woman.
لم أعد طفلًة، بل امرأةً شابة.
High on my newfound maturity,
منتشيًة ببلوغي الحديث،
I felt it was only natural to try drinking rum for the first time that night, too.
شعرت بأنه من الطبيعي أن أجرب شُربَ الرم في تلك الليلة أيضًا.
That was a bad idea.
وكانت تلك فكرةً سيئة.
I became very ill,
أصبحت مريضةً جدًا،
drifting in and out of consciousness
أتقلّب في نوبات من الوعي واللاوعي
in between spasms of convulsive vomiting.
بين تقلصات القيء المتشنّجة.
The security guards wanted to call me an ambulance,
أراد الحراس أن يطلبوا لي سيارة إسعاف،
but Tom acted as my knight in shining armor,
لكن (توم) تصرف كفارسٍ لي في درعه اللامع،
and told them he'd take me home.
وأخبرهم أنه سيأخذني إلى المنزل.
It was like a fairy tale,
كانت كقصة خيالية،
his strong arms around me,
ذراعاه القويتان تحوّطاني،
laying me in the safety of my bed.
ويضعني بأمانٍ في سريري.
But the gratitude that I felt towards him soon turned to horror
لكن الامتنان الذي شعرت به نحوه سرعان ما تحول إلى رعب
as he proceeded to take off my clothes and get on top of me.
حيث شرع في خلع ملابسي وصار فوقي.
My head had cleared up,
أفاق عقلي،
but my body was still too weak to fight back,
لكن جسدي كان لا يزال أضعف من أن يقاوم،
and the pain was blinding.
وكان الألم شديدًا.
I thought I'd be severed in two.
ظننت أنني سأشق إلى نصفين.
In order to stay sane,
لكي أحافظ على قواي العقلية،
I silently counted the seconds on my alarm clock.
عددت الثواني بصمت على ساعة منبهي.
And ever since that night,
ومنذ تلك الليلة،
I've known that there are 7,200 seconds in two hours.
علمت أن هناك 7200 ثانية في ساعتين.
Despite limping for days and crying for weeks,
بالرغم من عرجي لأيام وبكائي لأسابيع،
this incident didn't fit my ideas about rape like I'd seen on TV.
لم تلائم هذه الحادثة أفكاري عن الاغتصاب مثل ما شاهدت على التلفاز.
Tom wasn't an armed lunatic;
لم يكن (توم) مسلحًا مجنونًا،
he was my boyfriend.
بل كان صديقي الحميم.
And it didn't happen in a seedy alleyway,
وهذا لم يحدث في زقاق منعزل قذر،
it happened in my own bed.
حدث هذا على سريري.
By the time I could identify what had happened to me as rape,
بمرور الوقت استطعت تحديد ما حدث لي بأنه اغتصاب،
he had completed his exchange program
كان قد أكمل برنامج التبادل
and left for Australia.
وغادر إلى إستراليا.
So I told myself it was pointless to address what had happened.
لذلك قلت في نفسي أنه لا فائدة من التبليغ عن ما حدث.
And besides,
وبجانب ذلك،
it had to have been my fault, somehow.
سيكون ذلك خطئي بطريقة أو بأخرى.
I was raised in a world where girls are taught
لقد نشأت في عالم حيث يتعلّم الفتيات
that they get raped for a reason.
أنّهن يُغْتصبن لسبب ما.
Their skirt was too short,
بسب تنورة قصيرة جدًا،
their smile was too wide,
أو ابتسامةٍ عريضةٍ جدًا،
their breath smelled of alcohol.
أو رائحة كحولٍ تفوح من أنفاسهم.
And I was guilty of all of those things,
وقد كنت مذنبًة في كل هذه الأشياء،
so the shame had to be mine.
لذلك كان لا بدّ أن يكون العار من نصيبي أنا.
It took me years to realize
استغرقني الأمر سنوات لأدرك
that only one thing could have stopped me from being raped that night,
أن شيئًا واحدًا فقط كان يمكن أن يحول دون تعرضي للاغتصاب في تلك الليلة،
and it wasn't my skirt,
لم يكن ذلك بسبب تنورتي،
it wasn't my smile,
أو ابتسامتي،
it wasn't my childish trust.
كما لم تكن ثقتي الطفولية.
The only thing that could've stopped me from being raped that night
كان الشيء الوحيد الذي يمكن أن يحول دون تعرضي للاغتصاب في تلك الليلة
is the man who raped me --
هو الرجل نفسه الذي اغتصبني --
had he stopped himself.
كان عليه أن يمنع نفسه.
TS: I have vague memories of the next day:
توم: إنّ ذكرياتي عن اليوم التالي مبهمة،
the after effects of drinking,
آثار ما بعد الشرب،
a certain hollowness that I tried to stifle.
وخواءٌ معيّن حاولت كبته.
Nothing more.
لا شيء أكثر من ذلك.
But I didn't show up at Thordis's door.
لكنّني لم أذهب إلى منزل (ثورديس).
It is important to now state
ومن المهم القول الآن
that I didn't see my deed for what it was.
أنّني لم أعي فداحة ما اقترفت يداي.
The word "rape" didn't echo around my mind as it should've,
لم تتردّد كلمة "الاغتصاب" في عقلي كما كان ينبغي لها أن تكون،
and I wasn't crucifying myself with memories of the night before.
ولم أعذّب نفسي بذكريات الليلة السابقة.
It wasn't so much a conscious refusal,
لم يكن ذلك إنكارًا متعمدًا،
it was more like any acknowledgment of reality was forbidden.
لقد كان أقرب بأن أي اعتراف بحقيقة الأمر كان محظورًا.
My definition of my actions completely refuted any recognition
تعريفي لأفعالي دحض تمامًا أي اعتراف
of the immense trauma I caused Thordis.
بالصدمة الهائلة التي سبّبتها (لثورديس).
To be honest,
لأكون صادقًا،
I repudiated the entire act in the days afterwards
لقد تنصّلت من الفعل بأكلمه في الأيام التالية
and when I was committing it.
وعندما كنت أرتكبه.
I disavowed the truth by convincing myself it was sex and not rape.
تنصّلت من الحقيقة بإقناع نفسي بأنه كان ممارسة للجنس وليس اغتصابًا.
And this is a lie I've felt spine-bending guilt for.
وكانت هذه هي الكذبة التي أشعرتني بذنب يقصم الظهر.
I broke up with Thordis a couple of days later,
انفصلت عن (ثورديس) بعد بضعة أيام،
and then saw her a number of times
ومن ثم رأيتها عدة مرات
during the remainder of my year in Iceland,
خلال الفترة المتبقية من سنتي في آيسلندا،
feeling a sharp stab of heavyheartedness each time.
شاعرًا بطعنة حادة من الكآبة في كل مرة.
Deep down, I knew I'd done something immeasurably wrong.
في أعماقي، كنت أعلم أنّني اقترفت شيئًا خاطئًا لا يغتفر.
But without planning it, I sunk the memories deep,
ولكن بدون تخطيط له، أغرقت تلك الذكريات عميقًا،
and then I tied a rock to them.
ومن ثم ربطتها بصخرة.
What followed is a nine-year period
ما تبع ذلك هو فترة التسع سنوات
that can best be titled as "Denial and Running."
التي يمكن أن يكون أفضل عنوان لها هو "الإنكار والهرب".
When I got a chance to identify the real torment that I caused,
عندما سنحت لي الفرصة لمعرفة العذاب الحقيقي الذي تسبّبت به،
I didn't stand still long enough to do so.
لم أقف طويلًا لأفعل ذلك.
Whether it be via distraction,
سواء كان ذلك عن طريق إلهاء،
substance use,
أو تعاطي المخدرات،
thrill-seeking
أو البحث عن الإثارة
or the scrupulous policing of my inner speak,
أو السيطرة الدقيقة على ضميري،
I refused to be static and silent.
رفضت أن أكون ساكنًا وصامتًا.
And with this noise,
ومع هذا التشويش،
I also drew heavily upon other parts of my life
التفتّ أيضًا إلى أجزاءٍ أخرى من حياتي
to construct a picture of who I was.
لبناء صورة عن الشخص الذي كنته.
I was a surfer,
كنت راكبًا للأمواج،
a social science student,
وطالب علوم اجتماعية،
a friend to good people,
وصديقًا لأناس طيبين،
a loved brother and son,
وأخًا محبوبًا وابن،
an outdoor recreation guide,
ومرشدًا ترفيهيا في الهواء الطلق،
and eventually, a youth worker.
وفي نهاية المطاف، شابٌ عامل.
I gripped tight to the simple notion that I wasn't a bad person.
تمسّكت بشدة بالفكرة البسيطة بأنني لم أكن شخصًا سيئًا.
I didn't think I had this in my bones.
لم أكن أعتقد أنّني أملك هذا بداخلي.
I thought I was made up of something else.
ظننت أنني خُلقت من شيء آخر.
In my nurtured upbringing,
في نشأتي التي ترعرعت عليها،
my loving extended family and role models,
عائلتي المُحِبّة وقدواتي،
people close to me were warm and genuine
والأناس القريبين لي كانوا ودودين وصادقين
in their respect shown towards women.
في احترامهم الذي يظهرونه تجاه المرأة.
It took me a long time to stare down this dark corner of myself,
استغرقني الأمر وقتًا طويلًا لأنظر لهذا الجانب المظلم من نفسي،
and to ask it questions.
وأطرح عليه الأسئلة.
TE: Nine years after the Christmas dance,
ثورديس: بعد تسع سنوات من رقصة عيد الميلاد،
I was 25 years old,
كان عمري 25 عامًا،
and headed straight for a nervous breakdown.
وفي طريقي إلى انهيار عصبيٍ.
My self-worth was buried under a soul-crushing load of silence
دُفن تقديري لذاتي تحت وطأة صمتٍ ساحقٍ للنفس
that isolated me from everyone that I cared about,
الذي عزلني عن كل من أهتم لأمرهم،
and I was consumed with misplaced hatred and anger
واستُهلكت بالكراهية الخاطئة والغضب
that I took out on myself.
الذي صببته على نفسي.
One day, I stormed out of the door in tears
في أحد الأيام، انسحبت خارجًا وأنا أبكي
after a fight with a loved one,
بعد شجارٍ مع أحد الأحبّة،
and I wandered into a café,
ودخلت هائمةً إلى مقهى،
where I asked the waitress for a pen.
حيث طلبت من النادلة قلمًا.
I always had a notebook with me,
دائمًا ما أحمل مفكرة معي،
claiming that it was to jot down ideas in moments of inspiration,
بدعوى أنها لتدوين الأفكار في لحظات الإلهام،
but the truth was that I needed to be constantly fidgeting,
ولكن في الحقيقة أنني احتجت أن اكون دائمة الحركة،
because in moments of stillness,
لأنه في لحظات السكون،
I found myself counting seconds again.
أجد نفسي أحصي الثواني مرة أخرى.
But that day, I watched in wonder as the words streamed out of my pen,
ولكن في ذلك اليوم، شاهدت الكلمات بذهول وهي تنهمر من قلمي،
forming the most pivotal letter I've ever written,
وتشكّل أهمّ رسالة كتبتها على الإطلاق،
addressed to Tom.
موجهة إلى (توم).
Along with an account of the violence that he subjected me to,
مع إشارة إلى العنف الذي أخضعني له،
the words, "I want to find forgiveness"
عبارة، "أريد أن أجد الصفح"
stared back at me,
نظرت إلىّ،
surprising nobody more than myself.
مفاجئةً لي أكثر من أي أحد.
But deep down I realized that this was my way out of my suffering,
ولكن في أعماقي أدركت أن ذلك كان طريقي للخروج من معاناتي،
because regardless of whether or not he deserved my forgiveness,
لأنه بغض النظر عمّا اذا كان يستحق عفوي،
I deserved peace.
فإنّني كنت استحق السلام.
My era of shame was over.
انتهت فترة شعوري بالعار.
Before sending the letter,
قبل إرسال الرسالة،
I prepared myself for all kinds of negative responses,
هيّأت نفسي لكل أنواع الردود السلبية،
or what I found likeliest: no response whatsoever.
أو ما وجدته الأكثر احتمالًا: لا استجابة على الإطلاق.
The only outcome that I didn't prepare myself for
كانت النتيجة الوحيدة التي لم أعد نفسي لها
was the one that I then got --
كانت التي حصلت عليها --
a typed confession from Tom, full of disarming regret.
اعتراف مكتوب من (توم)، مليء بالندم الخاضع.
As it turns out, he, too, had been imprisoned by silence.
كما اتضح، أنه أيضًا كان حبيس الصمت.
And this marked the start of an eight-year-long correspondence
ومثَّل هذا بداية ثماني سنوات من المراسلات
that God knows was never easy,
يعلم الله أنها لم تكن سهلةً قط،
but always honest.
ولكن دائمًا صريحة.
I relieved myself of the burdens that I'd wrongfully shouldered,
أعفيت نفسي من الضغوط التي كنت تحملتها بغير وجه حق،
and he, in turn, wholeheartedly owned up to what he'd done.
وهو بدوره اعترف بصدق عمّا فعله.
Our written exchanges became a platform
خطاباتنا المتبادلة أصبحت منصةً
to dissect the consequences of that night,
لشرح تبعات تلك الليلة،
and they were everything from gut-wrenching
وكانت كل شيء بدءاً من كونها بغيضه
to healing beyond words.
حتى كونها شافيةً لأبعد الحدود.
And yet, it didn't bring about closure for me.
ولكنها لم تكون خاتمةً لي بعد.
Perhaps because the email format didn't feel personal enough,
ربما لأن شكل البريد الإلكتروني لم يكن شخصيًا كفاية،
perhaps because it's easy to be brave
ربما لأنه من السهل أن تكون شجاعًا
when you're hiding behind a computer screen on the other side of the planet.
عندما تكون مختبئًا خلف شاشة الحاسوب على الجانب الأخر من الكوكب.
But we'd begun a dialogue
ولكنّنا بدأنا حوارً
that I felt was necessary to explore to its fullest.
شعرت أنه من الضروري أن نكمله إلى أخره.
So, after eight years of writing,
ولذلك، بعد ثمان سنوات من الكتابة،
and nearly 16 years after that dire night,
وما يقارب 16 سنة بعد تلك الليلة الأليمة،
I mustered the courage to propose a wild idea:
حشدت شجاعتي لأقترح فكرة جريئة:
that we'd meet up in person
أن نتقابل شخصيًا
and face our past once and for all.
ونواجه ماضينا مرةً واحدة وإلى الأبد.
TS: Iceland and Australia are geographically like this.
توم: آيسلندا واستراليا جغرافيًا هكذا.
In the middle of the two is South Africa.
وفي المنتصف تقع جنوب إفريقيا.
We decided upon the city of Cape Town,
فقررنا أن نتقابل عند مدينة كيب تاون،
and there we met for one week.
وهناك التقينا لمدة أسبوع واحد.
The city itself proved to be a stunningly powerful environment
أثبتت المدينة نفسها أنها بيئة فعّالة
to focus on reconciliation and forgiveness.
للتركيز على المصالحة والصفح.
Nowhere else has healing and rapprochement been tested
لا يوجد مكان آخر تم اختباره في في الشفاء والتقارب
like it has in South Africa.
مثل جنوب إفريقيا.
As a nation, South Africa sought to sit within the truth of its past,
كأمّة، سعت جنوب أفريقيا أن تتعايش مع حقيقة ماضيها،
and to listen to the details of its history.
وتنصت إلى تفاصيل تاريخها.
Knowing this only magnified the effect that Cape Town had on us.
معرفة هذا وحده عظّم تأثير كيب تاون علينا.
Over the course of this week,
وعلى مدار هذا الأسبوع،
we literally spoke our life stories to each other,
حكينا حرفيًا قصص حياتنا لبعضنا البعض،
from start to finish.
من البداية إلى النهاية.
And this was about analyzing our own history.
وكان هذا عن تحليل تاريخنا الخاص.
We followed a strict policy of being honest,
اتبعنا سياسة صرامة على أن نكون صادقين،
and this also came with a certain exposure,
وجاء ذلك أيضًا مع انكشاف معين،
an open-chested vulnerability.
نقاط الضعف المكشوفة.
There were gutting confessions,
كانت هناك اعترافات بغيضة،
and moments where we just absolutely couldn't fathom
ولحظات حيث كنّا لا نفهم مطلقًا
the other person's experience.
تجربة الطرف الأخر.
The seismic effects of sexual violence were spoken aloud and felt,
التأثير المدمّر للعنف الجنسي قِيل عاليًا وشُعِرَ به،
face to face.
وجهًا لوجه.
At other times, though,
في أوقات أخرى، رغم ذلك،
we found a soaring clarity,
وجدنا صفاءً يصل عنان السماء،
and even some totally unexpected but liberating laughter.
وفي بعض الأوقات ضحكات غير متوقعة تمامًا ولكن محرّرة.
When it came down to it,
وعندما يصل الأمرإلى ذلك،
we did out best to listen to each other intently.
فعلنا أفضل ما بوسعنا لنسمع لبعضنا البعض باهتمام.
And our individual realities were aired with an unfiltered purity
وبُثت حقائقنا الشخصية بصفاء غير منمّق
that couldn't do any less than lighten the soul.
والتي أنارة أرواحنا بالكامل.
TE: Wanting to take revenge is a very human emotion --
ثورديس: الرغبة في الانتقام هي عاطفة بشرية جدًا --
instinctual, even.
بل أنّها حتى فطرية.
And all I wanted to do for years
وكل ما أردت القيام به لسنوات
was to hurt Tom back as deeply as he had hurt me.
كان إيذاء (توم) بشدة مثلما آذاني.
But had I not found a way out of the hatred and anger,
إن لم أجد طريقةً للخروج من الغضب والكراهية،
I'm not sure I'd be standing here today.
لست متأكدة إن كنت سأقف هنا اليوم.
That isn't to say that I didn't have my doubts along the way.
لا يعني هذا أنه لم تساورني الشكوك طوال الطريق.
When the plane bounced on that landing strip in Cape Town,
عندما ارتدّت الطائرة على مهبط الطائرات في كيب تاون،
I remember thinking,
أتذكر أنّني كنت أفكر،
"Why did I not just get myself a therapist and a bottle of vodka
"لماذا لم أذهب إلى طبيب نفسي وأشتريت زجاجة فودكا
like a normal person would do?"
مثلما قد يفعل أي شخص عادي؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
At times, our search for understanding in Cape Town
في بعض الأوقات، بدى بحثنا عن التفاهم في كيب تاون
felt like an impossible quest,
وكأنّه أمرٌ مستحيل،
and all I wanted to do was to give up
وكل ما أردته هو أن أستسلم
and go home to my loving husband, Vidir,
وأرجع إلى منزلي وزوجي الحبيب (فيدير)،
and our son.
وابننا.
But despite our difficulties,
ولكن بالرغم من الصعوبات التي واجهناها،
this journey did result in a victorious feeling
أسفرت هذه الرحلة عن شعور انتصار
that light had triumphed over darkness,
أضاء نوره الظلام،
that something constructive could be built out of the ruins.
وأّن شيئًا بنّاءً يمكن أن يُشيد من تحت الأنقاض.
I read somewhere
قرأت في مكان ما
that you should try and be the person that you needed when you were younger.
أنك يجب أن تحاول أن تكون الشخص الذي أردت أن تكونه عندما كنت صغيرًا.
And back when I was a teenager,
وعندما كُنت في سنّ المراهقة،
I would have needed to know that the shame wasn't mine,
كنت أودّ أن أعرف أنّ العار ليس عليّ،
that there's hope after rape,
أن هناك أمل بعد الاغتصاب،
that you can even find happiness,
ويمكنك حتى العثور على السعادة،
like I share with my husband today.
كما أشاركها مع زوجي اليوم.
Which is why I started writing feverishly upon my return from Cape Town,
وهو السبب في أنّني بدأت في الكتابة حثيثًا حين عودتي من كيب تاون،
resulting in a book co-authored by Tom,
الشيء الذي نتج عنه كتابٌ ساهم في كتابته (توم)،
that we hope can be of use to people from both ends
والذي نأمل أن يكون مفيدًا للأشخاص من كلا الطرفين
of the perpetrator-survivor scale.
على مستوى الجاني والمعتدي.
If nothing else,
إن كان غير ذلك،
it's a story that we would've needed to hear when we were younger.
أنها القصة التي كنّا بحاجة لسماعها عندما كنّا أصغر.
Given the nature of our story,
ونظرًا لطبيعة قصتنا،
I know the words that inevitably accompany it --
أعلم الكلمات التي تصاحبها بالضرورة --
victim, rapist --
الضحية، المُغتَصِب --
and labels are a way to organize concepts,
والتسميات هي وسيلة لتنظيم المفاهيم،
but they can also be dehumanizing in their connotations.
ولكنها يمكن أن تكون مجرّدة من الإنسانية في مضامينها.
Once someone's been deemed a victim,
بمجرد إعتبار شخصٍ ما ضحية،
it's that much easier to file them away as someone damaged,
من السهولة بمكان تصنيفهم كشخص محطّم،
dishonored,
مُهان،
less than.
أقل شأنًا.
And likewise, once someone has been branded a rapist,
وبالمثل، في حال وصف شخص ما كمغتصب،
it's that much easier to call him a monster --
فإنّه من الأسهل بكثير أن ندعوه وحشًا --
inhuman.
مجرّد من الإنسانية.
But how will we understand what it is in human societies
ولكن كيف يتسنّى لنا أن نفهم ماهية الشيء في المجتمعات البشرية
that produces violence
الذي يوّلد العنف
if we refuse to recognize the humanity of those who commit it?
إن رفضنا الاعتراف بإنسانية أولئك الذين يرتكبونه؟
And how --
وكيف --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And how can we empower survivors if we're making them feel less than?
وكيف يمكننا تمكين الناجين إن جعلناهم يشعرون بأنهم أقل شأنًا؟
How can we discuss solutions to one of the biggest threats
كيف يمكننا مناقشة الحلول لواحد من أكبر الأخطار
to the lives of women and children around the world,
التي تهدد حياة النساء والأطفال حول العالم،
if the very words we use are part of the problem?
إن كانت الكلمات التي نستخدمها هي جزء من المشكلة؟
TS: From what I've now learnt,
توم: من ما تعلمت الآن،
my actions that night in 1996 were a self-centered taking.
كانت أفعالي في تلك الليلة من العام 1996 مفعمة بالأنانية.
I felt deserving of Thordis's body.
شعرت باستحقاقي لجسد (ثورديس).
I've had primarily positive social influences
لقد كانت لدي تأثيرات اجتماعية ايجابية في المقام الأول
and examples of equitable behavior around me.
وأمثلة على السلوك العادل من حولي.
But on that occasion,
ولكن في تلك المناسبة،
I chose to draw upon the negative ones.
اخترت الاستفادة من السيئة منها.
The ones that see women as having less intrinsic worth,
تلك التي ترى المرأة على أنها أقل شأنًا،
and of men having some unspoken and symbolic claim to their bodies.
وأن الرجال لديهم حق رمزي وغير معلن للمطالبة بأجسادهن.
These influences I speak of are external to me, though.
هذه التأثيرات التي أتحدث عنها غريبة عني، بالرغم من ذلك.
And it was only me in that room making choices,
وكنت أنا فقط في تلك الغرفة من يتخذ الخيارات،
nobody else.
لا أحد غيري.
When you own something
عندما تمتلك شيئاً ما
and really square up to your culpability,
وتستعدّ حقًا لاستحقاق اللوم،
I do think a surprising thing can happen.
أعتقد أن شيئًا مدهشًا يمكن أن يحدث.
It's what I call a paradox of ownership.
هذا ما اسميه بمفارقة الامتلاك.
I thought I'd buckle under the weight of responsibility.
ظننت أني سأنهار تحت وطأة المسؤولية.
I thought my certificate of humanity would be burnt.
اعتقدت أن شهادتي البشرية قد تحترق.
Instead, I was offered to really own what I did,
بدلًا من ذلك، عُرض على الاعتراف بما فعلت،
and found that it didn't possess the entirety of who I am.
ووجدت أنها لم تصادر مجمل ما أنا عليه.
Put simply,
ولكن ببساطة،
something you've done doesn't have to constitute the sum of who you are.
شيء قمت بفعله ليس بالضرورة أن يشكّل مجمل من تكون.
The noise in my head abated.
خفت حدة الضجيج في رأسي.
The indulgent self-pity was starved of oxygen,
سلب الأكسجين من الإشفاق المتساهل على الذات،
and it was replaced with the clean air of acceptance --
واستبدل بهواء القبول النظيف --
an acceptance that I did hurt this wonderful person standing next to me;
قبول أنني آذيت هذه الإنسانة الرائعة الواقفة إلى جواري؛
an acceptance that I am part of a large and shockingly everyday grouping of men
قبول أنني جزء من هذا الجمع الكبير والمريع من الرجال
who have been sexually violent toward their partners.
الذين مارسوا العنف الجنسي تجاه شركائهم.
Don't underestimate the power of words.
إياكم والاستهانة بقوة الكلمات.
Saying to Thordis that I raped her changed my accord with myself,
قولي (لثورديس) بأنّني اغتصبتها غيّر وفاقي مع نفسي،
as well as with her.
وكذلك معها.
But most importantly,
ولكن الأهم من ذلك،
the blame transferred from Thordis to me.
تحوّل اللوم من (ثورديس) إليّ.
Far too often,
في كثير من الأحيان،
the responsibility is attributed to female survivors of sexual violence,
تُلقى المسؤولية على الإناث الناجيات من العنف الجنسي،
and not to the males who enact it.
وليس على الذكورالذين ارتكبوه.
Far too often,
في كثير من الأحيان،
the denial and running leaves all parties at a great distance from the truth.
يترك الإنكار والهرب جميع الأطراف على مسافة بعيدة جدًا من الحقيقة.
There's definitely a public conversation happening now,
هناك بالتأكيد مناقشة علنية تحدث الآن،
and like a lot of people,
ومثل كثير من الناس،
we're heartened that there's less retreating
نحن سعداء بأن هناك انسحاب أقل
from this difficult but important discussion.
من هذا الحوار الصعب ولكن المهم.
I feel a real responsibility to add our voices to it.
أشعر بمسؤوليةٍ حقيقة لإضافة أصواتنا إليها.
TE: What we did is not a formula that we're prescribing for others.
ثورديس: ما فعلناه ليست طريقة نفرضها على الأخرين.
Nobody has the right to tell anyone else how to handle their deepest pain
ليس من حق أي شخص إخبار شخص آخر بكيفية التعامل مع أعمق آلامهم
or their greatest error.
أو أكبر أخطائهم.
Breaking your silence is never easy,
كسر حاجز صمتك ليس سهلًا على الإطلاق،
and depending on where you are in the world,
واعتمادًا على مكان وجودك في العالم،
it can even be deadly to speak out about rape.
قد يكون تحدثك علنًا عن الاغتصاب مميتًا.
I realize that even the most traumatic event of my life
بل أدرك أن الحدث الأكثر صدمةً في حياتي
is still a testament to my privilege,
لا يزال دليلًا على امتيازي،
because I can talk about it without getting ostracized,
لأنني أستطيع التحدث عنه بدون أن يتم نبذي،
or even killed.
أو حتى قَتلي.
But with that privilege of having a voice
لكن مع هذا الإمتياز بامتلاكي لصوت
comes the responsibility of using it.
تأتي المسؤولية باستخدامه.
That's the least I owe my fellow survivors who can't.
هذا أقل ما أدين به لرفقائي من الناجين الذين لا يستطيعون.
The story we've just relayed is unique,
القصة التي نقلناها لتونا فريدة من نوعها،
and yet it is so common with sexual violence being a global pandemic.
ومع ذلك فهي شائعة جدًا مع كون العنف الجنسي وباءً عالميًا.
But it doesn't have to be that way.
ولكن ليس بالضرورة أن يكون بهذه الطريقة.
One of the things that I found useful on my own healing journey
واحدة من الأشياء المفيدة التي وجدتها أثناء رحلتي للشفاء
is educating myself about sexual violence.
هو تثقيف نفسي عن العنف الجنسي.
And as a result, I've been reading, writing
وكنتيجة لذلك، ظللت أقرأ وأكتب
and speaking about this issue for over a decade now,
وتحدثت عن هذه القضية لأكثر من عقدٍ من الزمان،
going to conferences around the world.
والذهاب إلى مؤتمرات في جميع أنحاء العالم.
And in my experience,
ومن واقع تجربتي،
the attendees of such events are almost exclusively women.
الحضور لمثل هذه الفعاليات هم النساء على نحو حصري تقريبًا.
But it's about time that we stop treating sexual violence as a women's issue.
ولكن حان الوقت أن نتوقف عن معاملة العنف الجنسي على أنه قضية المرأة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
A majority of sexual violence against women and men
أغلب العنف الجنسي ضد النساء والرجال
is perpetrated by men.
يتم على أيدي الرجال.
And yet their voices are sorely underrepresented in this discussion.
ومع ذلك، أصواتهم مهمشة بشدة في هذا النقاش.
But all of us are needed here.
ولكننا بحاجة إلى كل واحد منّا هنا.
Just imagine all the suffering we could alleviate
ولكم أن تتخيلوا كمّ المعاناة التي يمكننا تخفيفها
if we dared to face this issue together.
إن تجرأنا على مواجهة هذه القضية معًا.
Thank you.
شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)